Guide to the Duke University Progress Pictures Collection, 1925-1932
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Duke University Progress Pictures collection 1925-1932
University Archives, Duke University
Duke Construction Company.
3.5 Linear Feet approximately 1000 Items
These photographs were taken during the initial construction of Duke University, 1925-1932.
There is one set of pictures for East Campus and two sets for West, and modern copy prints and copy negatives of some images. The collection includes approximately 1000 mounted images in two bound sets (copy 1 and copy 2), along several file folders of mounted and unmounted prints.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Duke University Progress Pictures Collection were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975 and a gift in 1993.
Historical Note
These photographs were taken during the initial construction of Duke University, 1925-1932. According to the specification books for individual buildings, the contractor was to "furnish to the Architect each month during the construction of the structure, three photographs in duplicate, showing the progress of the work during the preceding month, taken from three different points to be agreed upon and always from the same points. These photographs shall be 8 x 10 inch, mounted on linen, with a hinge on the left hand margin of the photograph."
The Duke Construction Company was formed in 1927 on the advisement of the Building Committee of the Duke Endowment. In a letter to Duke president R.L. Flowers, N.A. Cocke, Assistant Secretary of the Duke Endowment, wrote:
"It is hardly practicable to conduct the operations in the name of the trustees of The Duke Endowment for the reason that The Duke Endowment has no separate entity apart from the trustees, it not being a corporation. On the other hand while the title to the property is in Duke University the Will and Trust Indenture contemplate that the trustees shall erect the buildings for Duke University and turn same over when completed. With the idea, therefore, of establishing some medium for the purpose of carrying on this construction, it has occured to us that it would be wise to form a corporation, known as the "Duke Construction Company" for the sole purpose of constructing these buildings, with a nominal capital stock so that it will clearly appear that this corporation is merely an agency for carrying out this work."
The Duke Construction Company was active in the 1930s and into the 1940s, but it then became dormant and was officially dissolved in 1957.
Collection Overview
There is one set of pictures for East Campus and two sets for West, and modern copy prints and copy negatives of some images. One set of the West Campus images (#2) is not accessioned. The other (#1) was received from the estate of W.F. Lee, likely a son of Arthur C. Lee who was the chief engineer for the construction. It is the more complete set (A93-73: five volumes + 25 unbound prints).
Most of the prints are numbered and dated on the front in white ink, and many for West Campus have a number, date, and description of the verso. Some of the prints were made into glass slides; these slides are in the Frank Clyde Brown Papers.
The collection includes approximately 1000 mounted images in two bound sets (copy 1 and copy 2), along several file folders of mounted and unmounted prints. The images range in date from 1925-1932.
The work of at least three photographers is represented in the Progress Pictures. For the East Campus photos, there are prints having the same base number with an A or B suffix, but which were taken on different dates. Some are marked on the verso "from Ramsey Studio, Durham, N.C." and others "Whitney's Camera Craft Shop, 106 1/2 E. Main St., Durham". The "A" and "B" designations are not consistent, and we cannot say that Ramsey was photographer "A and Whitney "B". Ramsey’s work predominates in the early photographs and Whitney’s in the later. Whitney's work is also represented in the West Campus pictures.
Also in the West Campus mounted prints are pictures marked "C.W. Richardson, Photographer, Duke University" or "Richardson's Photo Service…" According to the Bulletin of Duke University, volume 24, no.7a "The first twenty years" a C.W. Richardson was a member of the staff of the medical art and illustration division, which was started in 1933 (p. 44) and which included photographers. There are also unmounted numbered and unnumbered prints taken by Richardson. Some of these prints are marked News Service or Alumni Affairs. Some mounted West Campus prints are not credited, or if they were stamped by the photographer, the stamp has been covered by the mounting linen. Among the unmounted numbered and unnumbered prints, some are stamped News Service or Alumni Affairs.
The Progress Pictures are offered in jpeg format but are also available as high resolution .tif files.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke Construction Company
Duke University -- History -- 20th century
Duke University -- West Campus
Duke University -- East Campus
Duke University -- Buildings
Construction
Related Material
Operations and Maintenance Dept. records, 1919-1957
Duke University Archives
Frank C. Brown papers, 1899-1943
Duke University Archives/Rare Book Manuscript, Special Collections Library
University Archives Photograph collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
University Archives Photographic Negative Collection, 1855-1995
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- East Campus
  Following the image number is the following information: image file name, date, description, building name (if applicable) and comment (if applicable).
  - 19250815EC0003.jpg (Image 1)
    - 1925-08-15
    - West side of site looking north
    - Campus View
  - 19250815EC0004.jpg (Image 2)
    - 1925-08-15
    - East side of site looking north, test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19250901EC0005.jpg (Image 3)
    - 1925-09-01
    - West side of site looking north showing excavation for library
    - Library, East
  - 19250901EC0006.jpg (Image 4)
    - 1925-09-01
    - East side of site looking north showing excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19250901EC0007.jpg (Image 5)
    - 1925-09-01
    - West side of site looking north showing excavation for library
    - Library, East
  - 19250901EC0008.jpg (Image 6)
    - 1925-09-01
    - East side of site looking north showing excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251001EC0009.jpg (Image 7)
    - 1925-10-01
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251001EC0011.jpg (Image 8)
    - 1925-10-01
    - East side of site looking north showing excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251001EC0012.jpg (Image 9)
    - 1925-10-01
    - West side of site looking north showing excavations
    - Campus View
  - 19251015EC0013.jpg (Image 10)
    - 1925-10-15
    - East side of site looking north showing excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251015EC0014.jpg (Image 11)
    - 1925-10-15
    - West side of site looking north showing excavations
    - Campus View
  - 19251015EC0015.jpg (Image 12)
    - 1925-10-15
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251015EC0016.jpg (Image 13)
    - 1925-10-15
    - West side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall
    - Campus View
  - 19251103EC0017.jpg (Image 14)
    - 1925-11-03
    - East side of site looking north showing excavation for Union with test walls in the the distance
    - Union, East
  - 19251103EC0018.jpg (Image 15)
    - 1925-11-03
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, excavations and test walls in the distance
    - Campus View
  - 19251103EC0019.jpg (Image 16)
    - 1925-11-03
    - West side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall
    - Campus View
  - 19251103EC0020.jpg (Image 17)
    - 1925-11-03
    - West side of site looking north showing foundations for Library
    - Library, East
  - 19251103EC0021.jpg (Image 18)
    - 1925-11-14
    - West side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, railroad track, footings for Carr Building
    - Carr
    - [Dated 1925-11-14 on Photo]
  - 19251114EC0022.jpg (Image 19)
    - 1925-11-14
    - East side of site looking north showing excavation for Union, test walls in the distance
    - Union, East
  - 19251114EC0023.jpg (Image 20)
    - 1925-11-14
    - West side of site looking north showing foundations for Library and dormitories
    - Campus View
  - 19251114EC0024.jpg (Image 21)
    - 1925-11-14
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, foundations for Science Building
    - Science
  - 19251203EC0025.jpg (Image 22)
    - 1925-12-03
    - West side of site looking north showing foundation for Library. tennis courts and Trinity Park School Buildings in the distance. Sign warns students to stay out of sites.
    - Library, East
  - 19251203EC0026.jpg (Image 23)
    - 1925-12-03
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library and Craven Hall, the Ark and Crowell Building and the foundations for Science Building
    - Science
  - 19251203EC0027.jpg (Image 24)
    - 1925-12-03
    - East side of site looking north showing work on foundation for Union; test walls, Bishop's House and another residence visible in background
    - Union, East
  - 19251203EC0028.jpg (Image 25)
    - 1925-12-03
    - West side of site looking north showing foundation for Carr Building
    - Carr
  - 19251215EC0029.jpg (Image 26)
    - 1925-12-16
    - East side of site looking north showing Alspaugh, old Library, Craven Hall, Crowell Building, the Ark and the foundation for Science Building
    - Science
    - [Dated 1925-12-16 on Photo]
  - 19251215EC0030.jpg (Image 27)
    - 1925-12-16
    - West side of site looking north showing foundation for Library, tennis courts and Trinity Park School Buildings in distance. Sign warns students to stay out of sites.
    - Library, East
    - [Dated 1925-12-16 on Photo]
  - 19251215EC0031.jpg (Image 28)
    - 1925-12-16
    - East side of site looking north showing work on foundation for Union. Test walls, Bishop's House and another residence are visible in background.
    - Union, East
    - [Dated 1925-12-16 on Photo]
  - 19251215EC0032.jpg (Image 29)
    - 1925-12-16
    - West side of site looking north showing foundation for Carr Building
    - Carr
    - [Dated 1925-12-16 on Photo]
  - 19251217EC0033.jpg (Image 30)
    - 1925-12-17
    - Foundations for Library and Alspaugh. Flowers House, Dean's residence, gymnasium and Erwin Mills in background.
    - Campus View
  - 19251217EC0034.jpg (Image 31)
    - 1925-12-17
    - Foundation for Bassett House
    - Bassett
  - 19251217EC0035.jpg (Image 32)
    - 1925-12-17
    - Foundations for Alspaugh and Pegram Houses
    - Dormitories
  - 19251217EC0036.jpg (Image 33)
    - 1925-12-17
    - Foundations for Union and Brown house; Ark and Crowell in background
    - Union, East
  - 19260102EC0037.jpg (Image 34)
    - 1926-01-02
    - Foundation of Carr Building
    - Carr
  - 19260102EC0038.jpg (Image 35)
    - 1926-01-02
    - Foundation for Library
    - Library, East
  - 19260102EC0039.jpg (Image 36)
    - 1926-01-02
    - Foundation for Union
    - Union, East
  - 19260102EC0040.jpg (Image 37)
    - 1926-01-02
    - West side of site looking northwest showing foundations for dormitories
    - Campus View
  - 19260102EC0041.jpg (Image 38)
    - 1926-01-02
    - East side of site looking southeast showing work on foundations for Union and dormitories
  - 19260102EC0042.jpg (Image 39)
    - 1926-01-02
    - West side of site looking southwest showing foundations for dormitories; Alumni Memorial Gym in background.
  - 19260102EC0043.jpg (Image 40)
    - 1926-01-02
    - East side of site looking northeast showing work on foundation for Union; test walls, Bishop's House visible in background.
  - 19260102EC0044.jpg (Image 41)
    - 1926-01-02
    - East side of site looking northeast showing work on foundation for Union; test walls, Bishop's House visible in background.
    - There are two prints numbered 44
  - 19260102EC0045A.jpg (Image 42)
    - 1926-01-15
    - East side of site looking northeast showing work on foundation for dormitories.
    - [Dated 1926-01-15 on Photo]
  - 19260115EC0046A.jpg (Image 43)
    - 1926-01-15
    - West side of site looking northwest showing foundations for Library and dormitories.
    - Campus View
  - 19260115EC0047B.jpg (Image 44)
    - 1926-01-15
    - Foundation of Union Building
    - Union, East
  - 19260115EC0048A.jpg (Image 45)
    - 1926-01-15
    - West side of site looking southwest showing foundations for dormitories; Alumni Memorial Gym in background.
  - 19260115EC0049A.jpg (Image 46)
    - 1926-01-15
    - West side of site looking northwest showing foundations for dormitories.
  - 19260115EC0050A.jpg (Image 47)
    - 1926-01-15
    - East side of site looking east showing foundation for Union; Ark and Crowell Science at far right.
  - 19260115EC0051A.jpg (Image 48)
    - 1926-01-15
    - West side of site looking north showing foundations for dormitories; 1903 Library in background.
  - 19260115EC0052A.jpg (Image 49)
    - 1926-01-15
    - East side of site looking north showing foundation for dormitory. Library, Alspaugh Buildings left, Ark and Crowell Science Buildings, right.
  - 19260201EC0045B.jpg (Image 50)
    - 1926-01-15
    - East side of site looking south showing foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background.
  - 19260201EC0046B.jpg (Image 51)
    - 1926-02-01
    - West side of site looking northwest showing foundation for Library
  - 19260201EC0047A.jpg (Image 52)
    - 1926-02-01
    - East side of site looking south showing foundation for Science Building; Aycock and East Duke Buildings in background.
  - 19260201EC0048B.jpg (Image 53)
    - 1926-02-01
    - East side of site looking southeast showing steelwork for dormitory; Ark and Crowell Science in background.
  - 19260201EC0049B.jpg (Image 54)
    - 1926-02-01
    - East side of site looking southwest showing steelwork for dormitory
  - 19260201EC0050B.jpg (Image 55)
    - 1926-02-01
    - North end of site looking south showing foundation for Auditorium
    - Baldwin Auditorium
  - 19260201EC0051B.jpg (Image 56)
    - 1926-02-01
    - Center of site looking north showing foundation of Library and framing for dormitory (Alspaugh House)
  - 19260201EC0052.jpg (Image 57)
    - 1926-02-01
    - East side of site looking north showing foundations for dormitories; Bishop's House right rear
  - 19260201EC0052B.jpg (Image 58)
    - 1926-02-01
    - East side of site looking north showing foundations for dormitories; Bishop's House right rear
  - 19260215EC0053.jpg (Image 59)
    - 1926-02-15
    - Center of site looking northeast showing framing of dormitory (Bassett House)
  - 19260215EC0054.jpg (Image 60)
    - 1926-02-15
    - Center of site looking northwest showing framing of dormitories (Alspaugh and Pegram)
  - 19260215EC0055.jpg (Image 61)
    - 1926-02-15
    - East side of site looking south; foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background
  - 19260215EC0056.jpg (Image 62)
    - 1926-02-15
    - West side of site looking northwest
  - 19260215EC0057.jpg (Image 63)
    - 1926-02-15
    - East side of site looking northeast showing foundations and framing for dormitories
  - 19260215EC0058.jpg (Image 64)
    - 1926-02-15
    - West side of site looking southwest; gym and houses in background
  - 19260215EC0059.jpg (Image 65)
    - 1926-02-15
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building. Epworth, Aycock, and East Duke in background
  - 19260215EC0060.jpg (Image 66)
    - 1926-02-15
    - North end of site looking northeast showing foundation for Auditorium
  - 19260301EC0061.jpg (Image 67)
    - 1926-03-01
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building. Epworth, Aycock, and East Duke in background
  - 19260301EC0062.jpg (Image 68)
    - 1926-03-01
    - East side of site looking northeast showing framing for dormitories
  - 19260301EC0063.jpg (Image 69)
    - 1926-03-01
    - East side of site looking south; foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background
  - 19260301EC0064.jpg (Image 70)
    - 1926-03-01
    - West side of site looking southeast showing brickwork of Library; gymnasium and houses in the background
  - 19260301EC0065.jpg (Image 71)
    - 1926-03-01
    - West side of site looking northwest showing brickwork of Library and dormitory
  - 19260301EC0066.jpg (Image 72)
    - 1926-03-01
    - West side of site looking northwest showing boxcar and track-mounted crane; Library and dormitory in rear.
  - 19260301EC0067.jpg (Image 73)
    - 1926-03-01
    - East side of site looking north showing foundation of Union and steel framing for dormitory
    - Dormitories
  - 19260301EC0068.jpg (Image 74)
    - 1926-03-01
    - North end of site looking northeast showing foundation for Auditorium
    - Baldwin Auditorium
  - 19260316EC0069.jpg (Image 75)
    - 1926-03-16
    - Center of site looking northwest showing masonry work on Library and dormitory
    - Library, East
  - 19260316EC0070.jpg (Image 76)
    - 1926-03-16
    - East side of site looking south; foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background
    - Carr
  - 19260316EC0071.jpg (Image 77)
    - 1926-03-16
    - Middle of site looking southwest showing crane, supplies, and brickwork on Library; gymnasium in background
    - Library, East
  - 19260316EC0072.jpg (Image 78)
    - 1926-03-16
    - East side of site looking northeast showing railroad cars and framing of dormitory
  - 19260316EC0073.jpg (Image 79)
    - 1926-03-16
    - East side of site looking northeast showing foundation of Union and framing for Brown House dormitory
  - 19260316EC0074.jpg (Image 80)
    - 1926-03-16
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation of Science Building, Aycock, Epworth in background.
  - 19260316EC0075.jpg (Image 81)
    - 1926-03-16
    - West side of site looking northwest showing brickwork of Alspaugh and Pegram dormitories; Library at far left.
  - 19260316EC0076.jpg (Image 82)
    - 1926-03-16
    - Middle of site looking northeast showing foundation of Auditorium
  - 19260401EC0077.jpg (Image 83)
    - 1926-04-01
    - Middle of site looking northeast showing foundation of Auditorium
  - 19260401EC0078.jpg (Image 84)
    - 1926-04-01
    - West side of site looking west showing brickwork of Library
  - 19260401EC0079.jpg (Image 85)
    - 1926-04-01
    - West side of site looking north showing Library and Alspaugh and Pegram dormitories
  - 19260401EC0080.jpg (Image 86)
    - 1926-04-01
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation of Science Building, Aycock, Epworth in background.
  - 19260401EC0081.jpg (Image 87)
    - 1926-04-01
    - East side of site looking northeast showing foundation of Union and brickwork and framing of Brown House dormitory
  - 19260401EC0082.jpg (Image 88)
    - 1926-04-01
    - Center of site looking northeast showing framing and masonry of dormitories and foundation of Union at right.
  - 19260401EC0083.jpg (Image 89)
    - 1926-04-01
    - Center of site looking northwest showing work on Library and dormitories
  - 19260401EC0084.jpg (Image 90)
    - 1926-04-01
    - East side of site looking south; foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background
  - 19260415EC0085.jpg (Image 91)
    - 1926-04-15
    - Center of site looking northwest showing work on Library and dormitories
  - 19260415EC0086.jpg (Image 92)
    - 1926-04-15
    - East side of site looking north showing foundation and framing of Union Building and dormitories
  - 19260415EC0087.jpg (Image 93)
    - 1926-04-15
    - Center of site looking southwest showing scaffolding and masonry work on Library
    - Library, East
  - 19260415EC0088.jpg (Image 94)
    - 1926-04-15
    - Foundations of Auditorium, looking northeast
  - not yet scanned
    - 1926-04-15
    - Center of site looking southeast showing scaffolding of Science Building; Aycock and Epwoth in background
  - 19260415EC0090.jpg (Image 95)
    - 1926-04-15
    - East side of site looking south; foundation for Carr Building. Jarvis and West Duke Buildings in background
  - 19260415EC0091.jpg (Image 96)
    - 1926-04-15
    - Center of site looking northwest showing scaffolding and masonry work on Library
  - 19260415EC0092.jpg (Image 97)
    - 1926-04-15
    - Center of site looking northeast showing railcars, masonry work on dormitories (Bassett and Brown)
  - 19260601EC0115.jpg (Image 98)
    - 1926-06-01
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building. Epworth, Aycock, and East Duke in background
  - 19260601EC0116.jpg (Image 99)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Center of site looking northeast showing railcars, masonry work on dormitories (Bassett and Brown)
  - 19260601EC0117.jpg (Image 100)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Scaffolding and masonry on Carr Building
  - 19260601EC0118.jpg (Image 101)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Center of site looking northeast showing masonry and framing of dormitories (Bassett and Brown)
    - Dormitories
  - 19260601EC0119.jpg (Image 102)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Center of site looking southwest showing crane, scaffolding, and masonry work on Library.
    - Library, East
  - 19260601EC0120.jpg (Image 103)
    - 1926-06-01
    - North end of site looking east showing Bassett dormitory, foundation of Auditorium, railcar
    - Bassett
  - 19260601EC0121.jpg (Image 104)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Center of site looking northwest showing work on Library and Alspaugh dormitory
    - Library, East
  - 19260601EC0122.jpg (Image 105)
    - 1926-06-01
    - Foundations of Auditorium, looking northeast
  - 19260601EC0193.jpg (Image 106)
    - 1926-06-01
    - East campus Union with Brown House in background
    - Union, East
  - 19260615EC0123.jpg (Image 107)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Center of site looking northeast showing Alspaugh and Pegram dormitories
  - 19260615EC0124.jpg (Image 108)
    - 1926-06-15
    - East side of site looking north showing work on Union Building and Brown House dormitory in background
  - 19260615EC0125.jpg (Image 109)
    - 1926-06-15
    - East side of site looking southeast showing foundation for Science Building. Epworth, Aycock, and East Duke in background
  - 19260615EC0126.jpg (Image 110)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Foundations of Auditorium, looking northeast
  - 19260615EC0127.jpg (Image 111)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Masonry work on Carr Building, west side of site looking south
    - Carr
  - 19260615EC0128.jpg (Image 112)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Masonry work on Bassett House, foundation of Auditorium, north center of site looking east
    - Bassett
  - 19260615EC0129.jpg (Image 113)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Scaffolding and masonry work on Library, center of site looking southwest
    - Library, East
  - 19260615EC0130.jpg (Image 114)
    - 1926-06-15
    - Center of site looking northeast showing railcars, masonry work on Union, Bassett and Brown
    - Campus View
  - 19260615EC0131.jpg (Image 115)
    - 1926-06-15